<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<?xml-model href="rfc7991bis.rnc"?>
<rfc xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude"
     category="exp" docName="draft-ferro-apertomemory-00"
     ipr="trust200902" obsoletes="" updates="" submissionType="IETF"
     xml:lang="en" version="3" tocInclude="true" sortRefs="true" symRefs="true">

  <front>
    <title abbrev="ApertoMemory">The ApertoMemory Format: Portable,
    Client-Side-Encrypted AI Memory</title>
    <seriesInfo name="Internet-Draft" value="draft-ferro-apertomemory-00"/>
    <author fullname="Andrea Ferro" initials="A." surname="Ferro">
      <address>
        <postal><country>IT</country></postal>
        <email>irn@irn3.com</email>
      </address>
    </author>
    <date year="2026" month="July" day="19"/>
    <area>sec</area>
    <keyword>AI memory</keyword>
    <keyword>portability</keyword>
    <keyword>encryption</keyword>
    <keyword>COSE</keyword>

    <abstract>
      <t>AI assistants and agents accumulate long-term memory about their
      users. This memory is typically stored in proprietary, provider-held
      silos: it cannot be moved between tools, its integrity cannot be
      verified, and its confidentiality depends entirely on the provider.
      This document specifies the ApertoMemory format: a canonical,
      signed, client-side-encrypted representation of AI memory objects,
      together with a portable single-file export container. Memory
      objects are encoded in deterministic CBOR, signed with COSE_Sign1,
      and encrypted with COSE_Encrypt0 under keys derived from and
      controlled by the user. A storage or synchronisation server handling
      ApertoMemory objects has zero access to their content, authorship,
      or semantic timestamps.</t>
    </abstract>
  </front>

  <middle>
    <section anchor="intro">
      <name>Introduction</name>
      <t>Modern AI tools build user-specific memory: preferences, facts,
      learned behaviours, and procedural knowledge that improve the
      quality of assistance over time. This memory constitutes some of the
      most sensitive personal data in existence, and it is currently
      locked inside each provider's infrastructure. Switching tools
      destroys accumulated context, creating a form of vendor lock-in that
      operates on personal data rather than on price or features.</t>
      <t>Existing portability efforts move memory as cleartext JSON with
      no integrity protection, no verifiable provenance, and no
      confidentiality guarantees against the storage layer. This document
      takes the opposite starting point: memory is encrypted and signed on
      the user's device before it goes anywhere, and every party except
      the user's own runtime is treated as untrusted.</t>
      <t>This document specifies (1) the memory object data model and its
      deterministic CBOR encoding, (2) the cryptographic envelope
      (sign-then-encrypt with COSE), (3) the user-controlled key
      hierarchy including per-scope access separation, and (4) the
      portable export container. Synchronisation protocols and memory
      extraction from conversations are out of scope.</t>
      <section anchor="terms">
        <name>Terminology</name>
        <t>The key words "MUST", "MUST NOT", "REQUIRED", "SHALL", "SHALL
        NOT", "SHOULD", "SHOULD NOT", "RECOMMENDED", "NOT RECOMMENDED",
        "MAY", and "OPTIONAL" in this document are to be interpreted as
        described in BCP 14 <xref target="RFC2119"/> <xref
        target="RFC8174"/> when, and only when, they appear in all
        capitals, as shown here.</t>
        <dl>
          <dt>Memory Object</dt><dd>A single unit of AI memory (a fact,
          preference, event, or procedure) with metadata.</dd>
          <dt>Producer</dt><dd>Software that creates and seals Memory
          Objects on behalf of the user.</dd>
          <dt>Consumer</dt><dd>Software that opens Memory Objects and uses
          them to inform AI behaviour.</dd>
          <dt>Scope</dt><dd>A named partition of memory with its own
          encryption key, enabling per-tool access control.</dd>
          <dt>Blind Server</dt><dd>A storage or synchronisation server
          that handles sealed objects without the ability to decrypt
          them.</dd>
          <dt>DEK / KEK</dt><dd>Data Encryption Key (per object) / Key
          Encryption Key (per scope).</dd>
        </dl>
      </section>
    </section>

    <section anchor="model">
      <name>Data Model</name>
      <t>A sealed Memory Object is a CBOR map containing exactly the
      fields a Blind Server is permitted to see, plus an encrypted
      envelope. All semantic content, including authorship and semantic
      timestamps, lives inside the envelope.</t>
      <t>The normative schema is expressed in CDDL <xref
      target="RFC8610"/>:</t>
      <sourcecode type="cddl"><![CDATA[
sealed-object = {
  1 => bstr .size 16,   ; id: 128-bit random
  2 => bstr .size 16,   ; scope_id: opaque random identifier
  3 => uint,            ; format_version (this document: 1)
  4 => bstr,            ; COSE_Encrypt0 whose plaintext is a
                        ;   COSE_Sign1 over memory-payload
  ? 5 => bstr .size 16, ; dek_wrap_ref (optional)
}

memory-payload = {
  1 => mem-type,
  2 => tstr,            ; content (UTF-8 text)
  3 => confidence,      ; 0.0 .. 1.0
  4 => provenance,
  5 => trust-level,
  ? 6 => [* tstr],      ; tags
  7 => timestamps,      ; semantic times: MUST NOT appear
                        ;   outside the envelope
  ? 8 => embedding,     ; MUST NOT appear outside the envelope
  ? 9 => time,          ; expires_at
  ? 10 => {* tstr => any}, ; extensions
}

mem-type = &( episodic: 1, semantic: 2, procedural: 3 )
confidence = float .ge 0.0 .le 1.0
provenance = {
  1 => tstr,            ; producing tool identifier
  2 => bstr .size 8,    ; author_key_id: first 8 bytes of
                        ;   SHA-256 of author's Ed25519 key
  ? 3 => tstr,          ; session identifier
}
trust-level = &( self: 1, trusted: 2,
                 third-party: 3, unverified: 4 )
timestamps = { 1 => time, ? 2 => time }  ; created, updated
embedding = { 1 => tstr, 2 => [* float] } ; model, vector
]]></sourcecode>
      <t>Object identifiers MUST be generated from a cryptographically
      secure random source. Time-ordered identifiers (such as UUIDv7)
      MUST NOT be used, as they leak creation-time metadata to the Blind
      Server.</t>
      <t>Implementations MUST preserve unknown fields in the extensions
      map when re-encoding an object (see <xref target="versioning"/>).</t>
    </section>

    <section anchor="crypto">
      <name>Encoding and Cryptographic Envelope</name>
      <t>All structures are serialised as deterministically encoded CBOR
      as defined in Section 4.2 of <xref target="RFC8949"/>.</t>
      <t>The envelope construction is sign-then-encrypt:</t>
      <ol>
        <li>The memory-payload map is encoded as deterministic CBOR and
        signed as the payload of a COSE_Sign1 structure <xref
        target="RFC9052"/> using EdDSA (Ed25519).</li>
        <li>The COSE_Sign1 output is encrypted as the payload of a
        COSE_Encrypt0 structure using an AEAD algorithm under a
        single-use, per-object DEK with a 96-bit random nonce.</li>
      </ol>
      <t>Placing the signature inside the encryption prevents the Blind
      Server from learning or correlating authorship. Signature
      verification is performed by Consumers after decryption, and
      Consumers MUST reject objects whose signature does not verify.</t>
      <t>The mandatory-to-implement AEAD algorithm is AES-256-GCM (COSE
      algorithm 3). ChaCha20/Poly1305 (COSE algorithm 24) is OPTIONAL.
      Each DEK MUST encrypt exactly one object; nonce reuse under a given
      key is thereby structurally excluded, and the random nonce serves
      as defence in depth.</t>
      <t>All algorithms are referenced by COSE algorithm identifiers.
      Future migration (including to post-quantum algorithms) is a
      registry change, not a format change.</t>
    </section>

    <section anchor="keys">
      <name>Key Hierarchy</name>
      <t>All keys derive from, or are wrapped towards, material under
      exclusive user control:</t>
      <sourcecode type=""><![CDATA[
passphrase --Argon2id--> master secret (32 bytes)
master secret --HKDF-SHA256--> Ed25519 seed (signing)
master secret --HKDF-SHA256--> X25519 seed (key agreement)
scope KEK (32 bytes random)
    <-- ECDH-ES(X25519) + HKDF-SHA256 + AES-256-KW -- master
object DEK (32 bytes random, single object)
    <-- AES-256-KW -- scope KEK
]]></sourcecode>
      <t>The Argon2id <xref target="RFC9106"/> parameters are fixed for
      format version 1: memory 64 MiB, iterations 3, parallelism 4,
      16-byte random salt, 32-byte output (the second recommended
      parameter choice of RFC 9106).</t>
      <t>HKDF info strings provide domain separation:
      "apertomemory/v1/sign", "apertomemory/v1/ka", and
      "apertomemory/v1/kek-wrap" concatenated with the scope_id. Binding
      the KEK wrap to the scope_id ensures a wrapped KEK cannot be
      transplanted between scopes.</t>
      <t>Key wrapping uses AES Key Wrap <xref target="RFC3394"/>.
      Server-side key escrow is out of scope of this format: a lost
      passphrase without a recovery mechanism means unrecoverable
      memory, and implementations SHOULD offer user-held recovery codes.</t>
      <section anchor="scopes">
        <name>Scopes and Per-Tool Access</name>
        <t>Each Scope has its own KEK. A tool authorised for a subset of
        scopes receives only those KEKs and is cryptographically unable
        to open objects outside them. The scope_id visible to the Blind
        Server is an opaque random identifier carrying no semantic
        information about the scope's name or purpose.</t>
      </section>
    </section>

    <section anchor="export">
      <name>Portable Export Container</name>
      <t>The export container serialises a complete memory set into a
      single file (conventionally with the .amem extension):</t>
      <sourcecode type="cddl"><![CDATA[
amem-export = {
  1 => uint,              ; export_version (this document: 1)
  2 => vault-public,      ; salt, public keys, wrapped scope KEKs
  3 => [* bstr],          ; sealed-objects (encoded)
  4 => {* bstr => bstr},  ; object id => wrapped DEK
}
vault-public = {
  "salt" => bstr .size 16,
  "sign_pub" => bstr .size 32,
  "ka_pub" => bstr .size 32,
  "scopes" => {* tstr => scope-entry },
}
scope-entry = {
  "scope_id" => bstr .size 16,
  "kek_wrapped" => bstr,
  "eph_pub" => bstr .size 32,
}
]]></sourcecode>
      <t>The container holds only public keys, wrapped keys, and sealed
      objects; it is therefore safe to transport over untrusted channels.
      Possession of the file plus the user's passphrase is sufficient to
      reconstruct the entire memory on a new device.</t>
    </section>

    <section anchor="import">
      <name>Import Semantics</name>
      <t>Interoperability requires more than parseability. A Consumer
      claiming full conformance MUST take the type, confidence, creation
      time, and scope of memory objects into account when selecting which
      objects to surface to an AI system, and SHOULD prefer higher
      confidence and more recent objects when context is limited.</t>
      <t>Consumers MUST treat objects whose trust-level is not "self" as
      untrusted data: such content MUST be clearly delimited when placed
      in an AI context window and MUST NOT be given instruction-level
      privilege. See <xref target="poisoning"/>.</t>
    </section>

    <section anchor="versioning">
      <name>Versioning and Extensibility</name>
      <t>The format_version field governs breaking changes. Additive
      changes reuse the extensions map; implementations MUST preserve
      unknown extension fields when re-encoding, so that older tools do
      not destroy data written by newer tools.</t>
    </section>

    <section anchor="security">
      <name>Security Considerations</name>
      <section anchor="threat">
        <name>Threat Model</name>
        <t>This format protects memory at rest and in transit against:
        a compromised or curious storage/synchronisation server; the
        storage provider itself; and network observers. It intentionally
        does not protect against the AI runtime to which the user grants
        memory access (which must read cleartext to function), nor
        against malware on the user's own device. Specifications and
        products building on this format MUST NOT claim protections
        beyond this model.</t>
      </section>
      <section anchor="poisoning">
        <name>Memory Poisoning and Persistent Prompt Injection</name>
        <t>A memory object is text that will eventually be placed into an
        AI system's context. An attacker who can introduce objects into a
        user's memory achieves persistent prompt injection: instructions
        that resurface in every future conversation. This is
        substantially more dangerous than single-conversation injection.</t>
        <t>The format's mandatory signed provenance and trust-level field
        exist to mitigate this class of attack. Consumers MUST verify
        signatures before use, MUST NOT elevate non-"self" objects to
        instruction privilege, and SHOULD surface provenance to users
        when importing third-party memory sets.</t>
      </section>
      <section anchor="metadata">
        <name>Metadata Leakage</name>
        <t>A Blind Server still observes object counts, sizes, and
        synchronisation timing, from which usage patterns can be
        inferred. Semantic timestamps and embeddings MUST only exist
        inside the encrypted envelope. Implementations SHOULD pad sealed
        objects to size classes. Residual inference from traffic
        analysis is acknowledged and not fully mitigated by this
        format.</t>
      </section>
      <section anchor="embeddings">
        <name>Embeddings</name>
        <t>Embedding vectors permit approximate reconstruction of the
        text they were computed from. They are therefore content, not
        metadata, and MUST be encrypted like content. Server-side
        semantic indexing of embeddings is incompatible with this
        format's security goals; search is a client-side operation over
        decrypted objects.</t>
      </section>
    </section>

    <section anchor="privacy">
      <name>Privacy Considerations</name>
      <t>Erasure of an individual object is achieved by destroying its
      wrapped DEK (cryptographic erasure); the sealed blob becomes
      permanently unreadable even if retained by append-only storage.
      This provides a technical mechanism for erasure obligations such
      as those in data protection regulation.</t>
      <t>The export container is itself a data portability mechanism:
      it gives users a complete, machine-readable, provider-independent
      copy of their AI memory, aligned with portability rights such as
      Article 20 of the GDPR.</t>
    </section>

    <section anchor="iana">
      <name>IANA Considerations</name>
      <t>This document requests registration of the media type
      "application/amem+cbor" for the export container of <xref
      target="export"/>, following the template of <xref
      target="RFC6838"/>. Registration details will be completed in a
      future revision of this document.</t>
    </section>
  </middle>

  <back>
    <references>
      <name>References</name>
      <references>
        <name>Normative References</name>
        <reference anchor="RFC2119" target="https://www.rfc-editor.org/info/rfc2119"><front><title>Key words for use in RFCs to Indicate Requirement Levels</title><author fullname="S. Bradner"/><date month="March" year="1997"/></front><seriesInfo name="BCP" value="14"/><seriesInfo name="RFC" value="2119"/><seriesInfo name="DOI" value="10.17487/RFC2119"/></reference>
        <reference anchor="RFC8174" target="https://www.rfc-editor.org/info/rfc8174"><front><title>Ambiguity of Uppercase vs Lowercase in RFC 2119 Key Words</title><author fullname="B. Leiba"/><date month="May" year="2017"/></front><seriesInfo name="BCP" value="14"/><seriesInfo name="RFC" value="8174"/><seriesInfo name="DOI" value="10.17487/RFC8174"/></reference>
        <reference anchor="RFC8610" target="https://www.rfc-editor.org/info/rfc8610"><front><title>Concise Data Definition Language (CDDL)</title><author fullname="H. Birkholz"/><author fullname="C. Vigano"/><author fullname="C. Bormann"/><date month="June" year="2019"/></front><seriesInfo name="RFC" value="8610"/><seriesInfo name="DOI" value="10.17487/RFC8610"/></reference>
        <reference anchor="RFC8949" target="https://www.rfc-editor.org/info/rfc8949"><front><title>Concise Binary Object Representation (CBOR)</title><author fullname="C. Bormann"/><author fullname="P. Hoffman"/><date month="December" year="2020"/></front><seriesInfo name="STD" value="94"/><seriesInfo name="RFC" value="8949"/><seriesInfo name="DOI" value="10.17487/RFC8949"/></reference>
        <reference anchor="RFC9052" target="https://www.rfc-editor.org/info/rfc9052"><front><title>CBOR Object Signing and Encryption (COSE): Structures and Process</title><author fullname="J. Schaad"/><date month="August" year="2022"/></front><seriesInfo name="STD" value="96"/><seriesInfo name="RFC" value="9052"/><seriesInfo name="DOI" value="10.17487/RFC9052"/></reference>
        <reference anchor="RFC9106" target="https://www.rfc-editor.org/info/rfc9106"><front><title>Argon2 Memory-Hard Function for Password Hashing and Proof-of-Work Applications</title><author fullname="A. Biryukov"/><author fullname="D. Dinu"/><author fullname="D. Khovratovich"/><author fullname="S. Josefsson"/><date month="September" year="2021"/></front><seriesInfo name="RFC" value="9106"/><seriesInfo name="DOI" value="10.17487/RFC9106"/></reference>
        <reference anchor="RFC3394" target="https://www.rfc-editor.org/info/rfc3394"><front><title>Advanced Encryption Standard (AES) Key Wrap Algorithm</title><author fullname="J. Schaad"/><author fullname="R. Housley"/><date month="September" year="2002"/></front><seriesInfo name="RFC" value="3394"/><seriesInfo name="DOI" value="10.17487/RFC3394"/></reference>
      </references>
      <references>
        <name>Informative References</name>
        <reference anchor="RFC6838" target="https://www.rfc-editor.org/info/rfc6838"><front><title>Media Type Specifications and Registration Procedures</title><author fullname="N. Freed"/><author fullname="J. Klensin"/><author fullname="T. Hansen"/><date month="January" year="2013"/></front><seriesInfo name="BCP" value="13"/><seriesInfo name="RFC" value="6838"/><seriesInfo name="DOI" value="10.17487/RFC6838"/></reference>
      </references>
    </references>
    <section anchor="testvectors">
      <name>Test Vectors</name>
      <t>Machine-readable test vectors covering key derivation, the
      sealed-object construction, and the key hierarchy accompany the
      reference implementation. They will be inlined in a future
      revision of this document.</t>
    </section>
    <section anchor="ack" numbered="false">
      <name>Acknowledgments</name>
      <t>The memory-type taxonomy (episodic, semantic, procedural)
      follows established cognitive-science terminology also adopted by
      other AI memory efforts.</t>
    </section>
  </back>
</rfc>
